Guide to the University of Montana Photographs by Subject Collection 1895-1983
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
University of Montana photographs by subject collection
1895-1983
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
RG 6
5.5 linear feet
This collection contains a variety of photographs of events, people and locations at the University of Montana in Missoula.
Historical Note
The University of Montana in Missoula was founded in 1893 and opened to students on September 11, 1895. Oscar J. Craig was the institution's first President and there were four additional faculty members. From 1895-1898 classes were held in the South Side school on South Sixth Street. The cornerstone for University (Main) Hall was laid in 1898, but Science Hall was the first building on campus to be completed.
Although a comprehensive history of UM has yet to be written, H. G. Merriam's book The University of Montana: A History is a published source for information about university history up to the 1960s.
This is an artificial collection compiled around the subject of the University of Montana in Missoula. All of the images in this collection have something to do with University of Montana-related events, locations or individuals, and help to document over a century of campus history. Images come from a variety of sources. The majority of the images in this collection were placed in Archives & Special Collections prior to the 1980s. In many cases the original photographer and / or the provenance of an image is unknown.
Digital copies of the materials in Boxes 1 through 9 are available online at https://umt.box.com/v/RG006UMPhotographs. These digital copies were created in 2009 and are meant for reference only.
This collection has been arranged alphabetically by subject except in the case of oversized materials, which are located in the final box of the collection. Folders can contain one or more images related to that subject.
Researchers must use this collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
In most cases the chain of custody of an image is unknown.
The majority of the images were given to the Archives prior to the 1980s. Some of the images may have been removed from manuscript collections or university records at the time of their donation or transfer to the Archives.
University-related images may be added to this collection in the future. Documentation about the acquisition of an image will be maintained.
The Morton J. Elrod papers in Archives and Special Collections contain a large number of University of Montana images. Archives and Special Collections also holds collections of images by University Relations photographers and holds manuscript collections (such as the papers of an individual) that contain scrapbooks and photographs of university subjects and activities.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
University of Montana--Missoula--Photographs
Photographs
Montana; Missoula; Colleges and Universities
- Alumni: Distinguished Alumni Awardees, 1974-1984 and undated (Box-folder 1/1)
- Aerial and General Views, 1910-1965 and undated (Box-folder 1/2)
- Aerial and General Views, 1904-1968 and undated (Box-folder 1/3)
- Aerial and General Views, 1902-1957 and undated (Box-folder 1/4)
- Aerial and General Views-Mounted, 1905-1957 and undated (Box-folder 1/5)
- Athletics: Baseball, 1905-1936 and undated (Box-folder 1/6)
- Athletics: Baseball-Mounted, 1905-1908 and undated (Box-folder 1/7)
- Athletics: Men's Basketball, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
- Athletics: Football, 1897-1924 and undated (Box-folder 1/9)
- Athletics: Football, 1898-1903 (Box-folder 10 OS/5)
- Athletics: Football, 1898-1977 and undated (Box-folder 1/10)
- Athletics: Football-Boards, 1899-1927 and undated (Box-folder 1/11)
- Athletics: Football-Boards, 1899-1923 and undated (Box-folder 1/12)
- Athletics: Physical Ed. Class, 1922 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Athletics: Skiing, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
- Athletics: Track and Field, 1908-1918 and undated (Box-folder 2/3)
- Athletics: Track and Field-Boards, 1913-1926 and undated (Box-folder 2/4)
- Athletics: Water Ballet, undated (Box-folder 2/5)
  Aquamaids
- Athletics: Women's Basketball, 1905-1915, 1971 and undated (Box-folder 2/6)
- Athletics: Women's Field Hockey, undated (Box-folder 2/7)
- Athletics: Women's Softball, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
- Athletics: Women's Tennis, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
- Buildings: Brantly Hall, 1922 and undated (Box-folder 2/10)
- Buildings: Brantly Hall-Boards, undated (Box-folder 2/11)
- Buildings: Business, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
- Buildings: Cook Hall, 1920-1962 and undated (Box-folder 2/13)
- Buildings: Carillon, 1927 and undated (Box-folder 2/14)
- Buildings: Craig Hall, 1905-1923 and undated (Box-folder 2/15)
- Buildings: Craig Hall-Boards, 1904 (Box-folder 2/16)
- Buildings: Corbin Hall, 1926-1940 and undated (Box-folder 2/17)
- Buildings: Dornblaser Field, 1906 and undated (Box-folder 2/18)
- Buildings: Elrod Hall, 1922 (Box-folder 2/19)
- Buildings: Field House, 1953-56 and undated (Box-folder 2/20)
- Buildings: Forestry, 1916-1939 and undated (Box-folder 2/21)
- Buildings: Forestry Nursery, undated (Box-folder 2/22)
- Buildings: General, 1923 (Box-folder 10 OS/5)
- Buildings: Grizzly Pool, undated (Box-folder 2/23)
- Buildings: Heating Plant, 1922-1961 and undated (Box-folder 2/24)
- Buildings: Journalism, undated (Box-folder 2/25)
- Buildings: Jumbo Hall, 1961 (Box-folder 2/26)
- Buildings: Knowles Hall, undated (Box-folder 3/1)
- Buildings: Liberal Arts, 1960-1964 and undated (Box-folder 3/2)
- Buildings: Library, artist rendering of building not built, undated (Box-folder 10 OS/1)
- Buildings: Library, 1905-1957 and undated (Box-folder 3/3)
- Buildings: Library-Boards, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Buildings: Lodge, 1956-1960 and undated (Box-folder 3/5)
- Buildings: Lubrecht Forest, undated (Box-folder 3/6)
- Buildings: The "M", Mt. Sentinel Block House, 1928-1958 and undated (Box-folder 3/7)
- Buildings: Main Hall, undated (Box-folder 3/8)
- Buildings: Main Hall-Boards, 1904-05 and undated (Box-folder 3/9)
- Buildings: Memorials, undated (Box-folder 3/10)
- Buildings: Miller Hall, undated (Box-folder 3/11)
- Buildings: Music, undated (Box-folder 3/12)
- Buildings: Natural Science, 1921-27 and undated (Box-folder 3/13)
- Buildings: Performing Arts Radio/TV, 1982-1985 (Box 12)
- Buildings: Planetarium, 1955 and undated (Box-folder 3/14)
- Buildings: President's Home, 1913-1954 and undated (Box-folder 3/15)
- Buildings: Riding Arena, undated (Box-folder 3/16)
- Buildings: Schreiber Gymnasium, 1906-1961 and undated (Box-folder 3/17)
- Buildings: Schreiber Gymnasium-Boards, 1906 and undated (Box-folder 4/1)
- Buildings: Science Complex, undated (Box-folder 4/2)
- Buildings: Science Hall, 1900-1983 and undated (Box-folder 4/3)
- Buildings: Simpkins Hall, 1962 (Box-folder 4/4)
- Buildings: South Hall, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
- Buildings: Student and Faculty Housing, 1922-1961 and undated (Box-folder 4/6)
- Buildings: Student and Faculty Housing, 1921-1956 and undated (Box-folder 4/7)
- Buildings: Student and Faculty Housing-Boards, 1908 and undated (Box-folder 4/8)
- Buildings: Student Union, 1934 and undated (Box-folder 4/9)
- Buildings: Turner Hall, undated (Box-folder 4/10)
- Buildings: Women's Center (McGill), 1955 and undated (Box-folder 4/11)
- Buildings: Women's Gymnasium, 1904-1965 and undated (Box-folder 4/12)
- Building: Women's Gymnasium-Boards, 1905 (Box-folder 4/13)
- Buildings: Yellow Bay Bio Station, undated (Box-folder 4/14)
- Buildings: Yellow Bay Bio Station, 1921 and undated (Box-folder 4/15)
- Campus: aerial views, 1970 and undated (Box-folder 10 OS/3)
- Campus Visitors, undated (Box-folder 4/16)
- Chancellor, undated (Box-folder 4/17)
- Clubs/Orgs: ASUM, undated (Box-folder 4/18)
- Clubs/Orgs: Bear Paws, 1962 and undated (Box-folder 4/19)
- Clubs/Orgs: Dormitory group, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 10 OS/5)
- Clubs/Orgs: Druids, 1928-1953 (Box-folder 4/20)
- Clubs/Orgs: Engineers, undated (Box-folder 5/1)
- Clubs/Orgs: Fraternities and Sororities, 1906-1930 and undated (Box-folder 5/2)
- Clubs/Orgs: Fraternity (Alpha Kappa Psi), 1949 (Box-folder 10 OS/5)
- Clubs/Orgs: General, 1904-1922 and undated (Box-folder 5/3)
- Clubs/Orgs: General-Boards, 1920 and undated (Box-folder 5/4)
- Clubs/Orgs: Grizzly Riders, 1967 (Box-folder 5/5)
- Clubs/Orgs: Jubileers, 1956 (Box-folder 5/6)
- Clubs/Orgs: Kaimin, 1958 and undated (Box-folder 5/7)
- Clubs/Orgs: Kaimin-Boards, 1902 (Box-folder 5/8)
- Clubs/Orgs: Masquer Theater, 1924-1962 and undated (Box-folder 5/9)
- Clubs/Orgs: Mortar Board, 1961 (Box-folder 5/10)
- Clubs/Orgs: Order of the Grizzly, 1965 and undated (Box-folder 5/11)
- Clubs/Orgs: Phi Alpha Theta, 1961 (Box-folder 5/12)
- Clubs/Orgs: Spurs, 1947-1961 and undated (Box-folder 5/13)
- Clubs/Orgs: SS Music, undated (Box-folder 5/14)
- Depts/Schools: Art, 1962-1963 and undated (Box-folder 5/15)
- Depts/Schools: Drama/Dance, undated (Box-folder 5/16)
- Depts/Schools: Education, undated (Box-folder 5/17)
- Depts/Schools: Fine Arts, 1924-1931 and undated (Box-folder 5/18)
- Depts/Schools: Forestry, 1948-1959 and undated (Box-folder 5/19)
- Depts/Schools: Geology, undated (Box-folder 5/20)
- Depts/Schools: Geology-Boards, 1905 (Box-folder 5/21)
- Depts/Schools: Health Science, 1960-1964 and undated (Box-folder 5/22)
- Depts/Schools: Home Economics, undated (Box-folder 5/23)
- Depts/Schools: Journalism, 1918-1956 and undated (Box-folder 6/1)
- Depts/Schools: Law School, 1938-1963 and undated (Box-folder 6/2)
- Depts/Schools: Library, 1969-1983 and undated (Box-folder 6/3)
- Depts/Schools: Microbiology, 1964 and undated (Box-folder 6/4)
- Depts/Schools: Museum, undated (Box-folder 6/5)
- Depts/Schools: Music, 1907-1976 and undated (Box-folder 6/6)
- Depts/Schools: Music, 1920-1951 and undated (Box-folder 6/7)
- Depts/Schools: Music-Boards, 1908-1949 and undated (Box-folder 6/8)
- Depts/Schools: Nursery School, undated (Box-folder 7/1)
- Depts/Schools: Physical Therapy, undated (Box-folder 7/2)
- Depts/Schools: Physics, 1958-1964 and undated (Box-folder 7/3)
- Depts/Schools: Radio-TV, 1955-1962 and undated (Box-folder 7/4)
- Depts/Schools: Radio-TV-Boards, undated (Box-folder 7/5)
- Depts/Schools: Religious Studies, undated (Box-folder 7/6)
- Depts/Schools: ROTC, 1920 and undated (Box-folder 7/7)
- Depts/Schools: Sciences, 1907-1912 and undated (Box-folder 7/8)
- Depts/Schools: Sciences, undated (Box-folder 7/9)
- Depts/Schools: Yellow Bay Biological Station, 1903-1969 and undated (Box-folder 7/10)
- Events: Commencement, 1903-1956 and undated (Box-folder 7/11)
- Events: Forester's Ball, undated (Box-folder 7/12)
- Events: Homecoming, 1920-1963 and undated (Box-folder 7/13)
- Events: Institute on Indian Affairs in Montana, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 10 OS/6)
- Events: Interscholastics, 1911-1965 and undated (Box-folder 7/14)
- Events: Interscholastics-Boards, 1906 and undated (Box-folder 7/15)
- Events: Law Weekend, 1957 (Box-folder 8/1)
- Events: Library Conference, 1962 (Box-folder 8/2)
- Events: Library Kegger, undated (Box-folder 8/3)
- Events: Matrix Table, 1960 (Box-folder 8/4)
- Events: May Fête, 1917 (Box-folder 8/5)
- Events: Frank Milbum Memorial Fund, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 8/6)
- Events: Orientation Week, 1960 and undated (Box-folder 8/7)
- Events: Registration, 1948-1960 and undated (Box-folder 8/8)
- Events: Reunion, 1981-1995 and undated (Box-folder 8/9)
- Events: Sch. Admin. Leadership, 1960 and undated (Box-folder 8/10)
- Events: Summer Session, 1934-1948 and undated (Box-folder 8/11)
- Faculty and Staff, 1909-1976 and undated (Box-folder 8/12)
- Faculty and Staff, 1912 (Box-folder 10 OS/5)
- Faculty and Staff, 1929-1954 and undated (Box-folder 8/13)
- Faculty and Staff, 1906-1956 and undated (Box-folder 8/14)
- Faculty, E. Earl Bennett pencil sketch, undated (Box-folder 10 OS/2)
- Faculty and Staff-Boards, 1906 and undated (Box-folder 8/15)
- Presidents: Clapp, 1922-1935 (Box-folder 8/16)
- Presidents: Craig, 1909 and undated (Box-folder 8/17)
- Presidents: Craighead, 1912 (Box-folder 8/18)
- Presidents: Duniway, 1908 (Box-folder 9/1)
- Presidents: Johns, 1963 (Box-folder 9/2)
- Presidents: McCain, 1947 (Box-folder 9/3)
- Presidents: McFarland, undated (Box-folder 9/4)
- Presidents: Melby, 1942-44 (Box-folder 9/5)
- Presidents: Newburn, 1960 and undated (Box-folder 9/6)
- Presidents: Pantzer, 1959-1961 and undated (Box-folder 9/7)
- Presidents: Scheuch, undated (Box-folder 9/8)
- Presidents: Simmons, 1936 (Box-folder 9/9)
- Presidents: Sisson, 1919 (Box-folder 9/10)
- Students: Foreign Exchange, undated (Box-folder 9/11)
- Students: General, 1895-1942 and undated (Box-folder 9/12)
- Students: General, 1909-1952 and undated (Box-folder 9/13)
- Students: General, 1901-1919 and undated (Box-folder 9/14)
- Students: General-Boards, 1903-1938 and undated (Box-folder 9/15)
- Students: Rhodes Scholars, 1947-1970 and undated (Box-folder 9/16)